Guide to the Polish Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1926-1981 UA.40.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Polish Nationality Room Committee Collection
1926-1981
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Polish Nationality Room Committee.
UA.40.17
2.5 Linear Feet (4 boxes and 3 volumes)
The Polish Nationality Room Committee Collection details the planning, funding, construction, and dedication of the Polish Nationality Room. The majority of the documents range from 1926 to after the room's dedication in 1940. The collection contains correspondence, both between the committee members and with the Polish architect, as well as a running memo, newspaper clippings, photographs of the room and committee, finical statements, and other documents pertaining to the establishment of the Polish Nationality Room. A digital reproduction of a photo album is online.
Scope and Content Notes
The Polish Nationality Room Committee Collection details the planning, funding, construction, and dedication of the Polish Nationality Room in the Cathedral of Learning. The majority of these records range from 1926, when Chancellor John H. Bowman first approached the Pittsburgh Polish Community on the building of the Polish Nationality Room, to the dedication of the room in 1940. The collection contains general correspondence, much of which is between the Polish Committee and Ruth Crawford Mitchell, as well as the room's architect. Also included are photographs of the room and committee, newspaper clippings, memorial letters, dedication papers, a running memo, publicity materials, finical statements, committee minutes, and other documents related to the room and the Polish community in Pittsburgh. The materials are primarily in English, but some of the newspaper clippings are in Polish.
Existence and Location of Copies
A digital reproduction of a photo album is available online.
History
Though the idea of building a Polish Nationality Room first came up in 1925, it was only discussed in earnest in the late 1920s. Planning began in 1930 and the committee for the erection of the Polish Hall in the Cathedral of Learning was organized February 5, 1931. Fundraising for the room occurred until the German invasion of Poland in late 1939, when the Polish community focused instead on creation the Polish Emergency Relief Committee. The University of Pittsburgh provided the remaining funds for the construction of the Polish Nationality Room, which was dedicated on February 16, 1940, before a group of both American and Polish representatives.
The first chairman of the committee was Colonel Theophilus A. Starzynski, who served in that capacity until 1939. After him, Dr. Chester S. Sierakowski was appointed chairman and held that position until the end of World War II. The committee worked closely with both the Polish Women's League and Ruth Crawford Mitchell, who was the Advisor to the Nationality Rooms. The Polish Falcons of America and the Polish National Alliance of North America were also involved with providing publicity and funds for the establishment of the room. Professor A. Szyszko-Bohusz, a famous Cracow-based architect, provided the design for the Polish Nationality Room.
The room is designed in the style of the 1500s Polish Renaissance and was based on Wawel Castle, which overlooks the city of Cracow. The entrance door was carved out of oak by a Lwow craftsman and was gifted to the room by the Polish Women's Alliance. The cornerstone, presented by the faculty of the University of Cracow, is a fragment from the oldest university building in Poland, the Jagiellonian Library. Behind the professor's chair hangs an oil painting of the Polish astronomer Copernicus, a copy of a famous work by Anna Szyszko-Bohusz. Also in the room is the Jagiellonian Globe, a reproduction of a 16th century object that also serves as a clock and a calendar.
The Polish Room still provides a scholarship for students studying abroad in Poland, dedicated to the memory of Dr. Donald Mushalko.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into two series:
Series I. Room Construction and Dedication
Series II. Committee Administration
Acquisition Information
Transferred to the University Archives by the Nationality Rooms Program on August 3, 2014.
Previous Citation
Polish Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1926-1981, UA.40.17, University of Pittsburgh Archives
Minutes (Administrative records); Photographs; Polish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Clippings (Information artifacts); University of Pittsburgh; Correspondence; Financial records; Starzynski, Theophilus A.; Mitchell, Ruth Crawford; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Polish Nationality Room Committee.; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Room Construction and Dedication, 1926-1952; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series primarily consists of correspondence, publicity and memos documenting the efforts of the Polish Nationality Room Committee as they worked to fund, design and build the room in the Cathedral of Learning. Also included are some records pertaining to events hosted in the room after it was dedicated in 1940 which were stored with the earlier documents in elaborate enclosures that were to be kept in the Polish Room.
  - Deed of Gift for the Polish Room in the Cathedral of Learning, June 4, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Polish Classroom Booklet, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Colonel T.A. Starzynski Memorial Letter, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft of Speech for the Presentation of Three Volumes of "Manru" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reception For Professor Halecki, November 14, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reception for Professor Swietoslawski, Apri 19, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Christmas Supper Program (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cornerstone Laying Ceremonies of the Polish Room, June 26, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Presentation of the Portrait of Paderewski and Correspondence with Paderewski, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dedication Ceremony Papers, February 16, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Digest of Running Memo, 1926-1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Foreign and Architectural Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Jagellonian Globe Correspondence, 1931-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Life History of Henry Waldyn (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lists of Polish Coats of Arms and Seals (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Running Memo, 1927-1941 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Clippings and Publicity, 1933-1964 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Volume 3)
- Committee Administration, 1932-1981; II.
  This series includes committee correspondence and newsletters documenting their activities to maintain the Polish Nationality Room and provide programming after it was dedicated. Also included are histories that explore how the room came to fruition and files on the room's design that were not stored with the majority of the earlier records.
  - Polish Room Publicity (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Polish Room Newsletter, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Polish Room History (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Description of Room (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Memos on Design, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Committee Meeting Minutes, 1942-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Copernicus Quadricentennial, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Running Memo, 1942-1948 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Colonel T.A. Starzynski, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Polish Room Maintenance, 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Cabinet Dedication, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Nationality Rooms Director, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Polish Books, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Polish Room Committee Members and Officers, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - General Correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - General Correspondence, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - General Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1974-1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Polish Arts League, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Choir Reception, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Polish Room Committee Guest Lists (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Slavic Cultural Variety Program, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Polish Studies Seminar, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Polish Studies Workshops, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Piotr Janowski Concert, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - First Secretary Edward Gierek's Visit, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)